Edward W. Gilbert Papers VHP2004/10
CCSU Veterans History Project
Edward W. Gilbert Papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942-1945, 1986, 2004
VHP2004/10
CCSU Veterans History Project
22.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
Gilbert, Edward W.
Biographical/Historical note
Edward Gilbert was drafted into the United States Army in June of 1942. The Wethersfield, Connecticut native served overseas in the 2nd Engineer Boat and Shore Regiment in the South Pacific. He received his basic training at Fort Bragg in North Carolina and his amphibious training at Camp Edwards, Massachusetts, Washburn Island, Massachusetts, Martha’s Vineyard, Massachusetts, and Cairns, Australia. Edward served in the Philippines and Australia as the coxswain (driver) of Landing Craft 838. Achieving the rank of Technician 4th Grade, Sergeant Edward received the Good Conduct Ribbon and the Asiatic Pacific Ribbon with Arrowhead. He was honorably discharged in October of 1945
Scope and Contents note
This collection details Edward Gilbert’s military experiences during his enlistment in World War II. A taped interview was conducted on June 17, 2004 at Central Connecticut State University by Eileen Hurst. Along with Edward’s taped interview the collection contains reproductions of personal documents, publications and photographs. The materials provide evidence of the development of the U.S. Army’s “ship to shore” or amphibious landing crafts, enemy activity and engagement, amphibious training, and crew responsibilities.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 4 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Publications
Series IV, Multi-media
United States. Army. Engineer Boat and Shore Regiment, 592nd. Company B.; United States. Army. Engineer Special Brigade, 2nd.; Australia; Camp Edwards (Mass.); Fort Devens (Mass.); Landing craft; New Guinea; Philippines; World War, 1939-1945 -- Amphibious operations; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- New Guinea; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1942-1945 and 2004
  - Certificate of Achievement and Rank, September 15, 1942; 2004/10.I.1
  - Ancient Order of the Deep Certification (Shellback certificate), February 1, 1943; 2004/10.I.2
  - Edward Gilbert's Separation Qualification Record, July 1, 1945; 2004/10.I.3
  - Edward Gilbert's Certificate of Discharge, October 8, 1945; 2004/10.I.4
  - Form WD AGO 53-55 Enlisted Record and Reoprt of Separation, October 8, 1945; 2004/10.I.5
  - Interview Synopsis, June 17, 2004; 2004/10.I.6
  - Interview Transcript, June 17, 2004; 2004/10.I.7
- Series II: Military Documents, 1944
  - Yaleau Operation Landing Diagram, March 3, 1944; 2004/10.II.1
- Series III: Publications, 1945
  - Cape Cod as the Cradle of Invasion, Junr 22, 1945; 2004/10.III.1; 4.0 Digital objects
    General note
    The folder contains an article published in the Falmouth Enterprise titled “Cape Cod as the Cradle of Invasion.” The story, a component of the 14 part series from The Story of Camp Edwards from Scrub Pines to Medical Center, describes the development of the U.S. Army’s amphibious training, techniques and landing craft on the beaches of Cape Cod.
  - U.S. Army recruiting advertisement, Circa 1940s; 2004/10.III.2
    A U.S. Army recruiting advertisement published in the New York Times. The ad espouses the glory and thrill of Sea Taxis and the Army Engineer’s Amphibian Command.
- Series IV: Multi-Media
  - Subseries A: Still Images, 1942-1945, 1986
    - Sergeant Edward Gilbert kneeling, in uniform. Edward drove an amphibious landing craft for the United States Army during World War II, Summer 1942; 2004/10.IV.1
    - Landing Craft #209. Finch Haven, New Guinea, 1943; 2004/10.IV.2
    - Sergeant Edward Gilbert (right) and Stan Mowaki (left) standing in front of tent with knives in their belts, Between June 1943 and Oct 1945; 2004/10.IV.3
    - Sergeant Edward Gilbert standing in front of tent, Between June 1943 and Oct 1945; 2004/10.IV.4
    - Sergeant Edward Gilbert standing in front of tent. A soldier can be seen in the background lying on a bunk. Philippines, 1944; 2004/10.IV.5
    - Five people posing in a boat anchored in harbor. Romblon Island, Philippines, 1945; 2004/10.IV.6
    - Soldiers posing in front of tent while holding a snake. Left to right; Massachusetts, Philadelphia (was the barber), New York, and New Jersey. The soldiers used names of states as nicknames. Philippines., Between June 1943 and Oct 1945; 2004/10.IV.7
    - Enlisted man posing in Japanese plane. Mindoro, Philippines., Between June 1943 and Oct 1945; 2004/10.IV.8
    - Unused barracks at Camp Edwards. Cape Cod, Massachusetts, 1986; 2004/10.IV.9
  - Subseries B: Moving images, 2004
    - Oral History interview with Edward Gilbert, June 17, 2004; 2004/10.IVb.1; 2.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2004/10, Box Circulation #1)
      Existence and Location of Copies note
      Interview video also available online.
      Streaming Video